A Guide to the Governor James Patton Preston Executive Papers, 1816-1819
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor James Patton Preston Executive Papers, 1816-1819
Library of Virginia
41737
5.0 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Alternate Form Available
Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reels 6263A-6273
Miscellaneous Reel 6262A - Box 1, Folders 1-11 (1816 Dec-1817 Apr 15)
Miscellaneous Reel 6263B - Box 1, Folders 12-15 (1817 Apr 16-May 31)
Miscellaneous Reel 6264 - Box 2
Miscellaneous Reel 6265 - Box 3
Miscellaneous Reel 6266 - Box 4
Miscellaneous Reel 6267A - Box 5, Folders 1-8 (1818 June-July)
Miscellaneous Reel 6267B - Box 5, Folders 9-13 (1818 Aug-Sept)
Miscellaneous Reel 6268 - Box 6
Miscellaneous Reel 6269 - Box 7
Miscellaneous Reel 6270 - Box 8
Miscellaneous Reel 6271 - Box 9
Miscellaneous Reel 6272 - Box 10
Miscellaneous Reel 6273 - Box 11
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Biographical Information
James Patton Preston was born at "Smithfield" in Montgomery County, Virginia, on 21 June 1774, the ninth child of Colonel William Preston and Susanna Smith. He was educated at the William & Mary College from 1790 to 1795. In 1799, Preston qualified as justice of the peace for Montgomery County. He married Nancy Taylor of Norfolk, Va., sister of Gen. Robert B. Taylor, on 13 June 1801. One of Preston's six children, William Ballard Preston, became Secretary of the Navy in President Zachariah Taylor's Cabinet and a senator in the Confederate Congress. From 1801 to 1804, Preston served in the Virginia Senate. Preston also represented Montgomery County in the House of Delegates from 1810 to 1812. During the War of 1812, he was commissioned lieutenant colonel of the 12th U. S. Infantry. On 15 August 1813, he was promoted to colonel of the regiment and reassigned to the 23rd U. S. Infantry. Severely wounded at the battle of Chrysler's Farm on 13 November 1813, Preston was later discharged from the army on 15 June 1815.
Preston returned to politics with his re-election to the House of Delegates on 11 November 1816. This term in the House was extremely short-lived as he was elected governor on 11 December 1816 to succeed Wilson Cary Nicholas. Preston served the maximum three one-year terms as governor until 11 December 1819. Notable achievements during his governorship include the establishment of the University of Virginia, improvements to Capitol Square, and the charting of Virginia's rivers & counties. Following his governorship, President James Monroe appointed Preston postmaster for Richmond from 1824 to 1837. In 1837, he was chosen president of a convention at Abingdon to plan a railroad from Lynchburg to Tennessee. He died on 4 May 1843 and is buried at a family plot at "Smithfield." Preston County, West Virginia, was named in his honor in 1818.
Scope and Content
James Patton Preston's Executive papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during his three one-year terms as governor from 11 December 1816 to 11 December 1819. The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics including appointments & recommendations for state positions; repairs & improvements to the Capitol & Capitol Square; the Public Guard; the Lexington Arsenal; John Wood's surveys of Virginia's rivers & counties; the Virginia Penitentiary; the settlement of accounts of Virginia with the United States for expenses during the War of 1812; resignations; extraditions; state expenses & revenue; elections; and others. These papers are arranged chronologically with pardons arranged to the rear of each year. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from the Virginia Senate & House of Delegates; accounts; oaths; muster rolls; pardons; proposals; receipts; election returns; certificates; qualifications; petitions; reports; appointments; resignations; bonds; commissions; orders; proceedings; applications; and other sundry items. The Governor received correspondence from three main sources: the Federal government, Virginia State government, and Governors from other states.
Federal government correspondents include President James Madison; John Quincy Adams, Secretary of State; John C. Calhoun, Secretary of War; William H. Crawford, Secretary of the Treasury; James Barbour & Armistead T. Mason, Virginia's senators in Congress; and Henry Clay, Speaker of the House of Representatives.
President James Madison writes on 1 March 1817 enclosing his answer to the address of the General Assembly dated 10 February regarding his presidency. As Secretary of State, John Quincy Adams often transmitted recently passed laws of Congress. On 29 July 1817, Richard Rush, Acting Secretary of State, encloses a resolution of the Senate to prepare & report a statement relative to the regulations & standards for weights & measures which may exist in the several states. John Quincy Adams encloses a resolution of Congress proposing an amendment to the Constitution against citizens to accept titles of nobility from a foreign power without the consent of Congress (1818 Jan. 7). Adams also transmits thirty volumes of Wait's Edition of State Papers to Virginia (1818 Oct. 19), a copy of Seybert's Statistical Annals (1819 March 19), copies of the public journals of the Senate & House of Representatives (1819 July 19), and six sets of documents for distribution (1819 Nov. 8). John C. Calhoun, Secretary of War, writes to Governor Preston regarding an arrangement with the state of Virginia for a supply of arms (1818 May 6). William H. Crawford, Secretary of the Treasury, encloses the resolution of Congress that the Secretary transmit a general statement of the condition of the Bank of the United States & its offices (1819 July 23). James Barbour & Armistead T. Mason, Virginia's senators in Congress, write enclosing a letter from Daniel Pettibone requesting aid for his improvements in the welding of cast steel to iron (1817 Feb. 24). Lastly, Henry Clay, Speaker of the House of Representatives, writes regarding the death of Peterson Goodwyn, a Virginia Congressman (1818 March 19).
The majority of correspondence in James Patton Preston's Executive Papers originates from Virginia State government. Significant correspondents from Virginia State government include Orris Paine, Arthur S. Brockenbrough, & Wilson Bryan, Superintendents of Public Improvements of the Capitol Square; Thomas Strode, Paul A. Sabbaton, John P. Shields, George C. Longden, & James Kinkead, contractors on Capitol Square improvements; Claiborne W. Gooch, Adjutant General; James Paxton, Commandant of the Lexington Arsenal; Peter Crutchfield & Blair Bolling, Commandants of the Public Guard; John Staples, Superintendent of the Virginia Manufactory of Arms; Samuel P. Parsons, Keeper of the Penitentiary; Philip N. Nicholas & John Robertson, Attorneys General; William Munford, Clerk of the House of Delegates; William Robertson, Clerk of the Council of State; John Burfoot, Auditor of Public Accounts; John Wood, Surveyor; and John Chew, Commissioner appointed to settle the accounts of the Commonwealth with the Unites States.
Orris Paine, Arthur S. Brockenbrough, & Wilson Bryan all served as Superintendent of Public Improvements of Capitol Square during Preston's governorship. Orris Paine requests to have two models made regarding the manner of Godefroy's plan for the Capitol Square (1817 April 3). Paine also writes regarding the completion of one-third of the digging and filling up of the Capitol Square (1817 May 8). Additional correspondence from Orris Paine relate to the following subjects: the stone steps hammered by James Kinkead under the contract of Thomas Strode (1817 May 13); the work of John P. Shields in digging & removing the earth under the contract of Thomas Strode (1817 May 13); the roof of the Capitol (1817 May 14); repairs to the chimneys of the Capitol (1817 May 24); a skylight for the Capitol to light the garret & conference rooms in the southeast & northwest corners (1817 May 30); a report of repairs recommended to be done on the Capitol (1817 June 20); the recommendation of Godefroy to close up two windows in the pediment ends of the Capitol and the finishing of the dome under the skylight (1817 July 5); a copy of the orders in Council relating to the repairing of the Capitol & improving the Square since July 1816 (1818 Feb. 21); and his report on public property including the certification of accounts, the stone steps, furniture of the Capitol, etc. (1818 March 5). Paine continued to correspond with the Governor after his replacement as superintendent in the role as administrator of James Kinkead, one of the contractors who furnished granite for Capitol Square. On 2 June 1818, Paine requests an advance on the contract of James Kinkead, deceased, for furnishing the steps on Capitol Square. Paine also writes regarding the order drawn by Thomas Strode for $3,000 in favor of James Kinkead (1818 June 12); the steps furnished under contract with James Kinkead (1818 July 16); his proposal for leasing out the Foundry, Boring Mill, & waste water from the Armory (1818 July 18); the contract of P. A. Sabbaton for enclosing the Public Square (1818 Dec. 28); Richard North's letter regarding his bill for marble basins (1818 Dec. 30);, the balance due him for the steps contracted for by James Kinkead with Thomas Strode (1819 March 29); the certificate of A. S. Brockenbrough regarding the completion of the steps on both sides of the Capitol (1819 July 2); payment for his work to set the steps (1819 July 15); the certificate of A. S. Brockenbrough regarding the completion of three-fourths of the work around the Governor's lot (1819 Aug. 16); the certificate of A. S. Brockenbrough regarding the completion of the steps & ashlars around the Capitol (1819 Aug. 17); the entrance gate into the Governor's yard (1819 Oct. 2); the completion of the stone wall, capping stones, & brace stones (1819 Nov. 4); and the number of feet of railing required to enclose the Public Square & Governor's lot (1819 Nov. 16 & 30).
Arthur S. Brockenbrough replaced Orris Paine as Superintendent of Public Improvements in March 1818. Brockenbrough writes on 28 March 1818 regarding his proposal to undertake the superintendence of the gradation of the Public Square. In his letter of 3 April 1818, Brockenbrough encloses a sketch of Capitol Square along with an explanation of the enclosure around the Square. In addition, Brockenbrough corresponds with respect to the following subjects: the steps in the Public Square (1818 April 8); braces for the enclosure around the Public Square (1818 April 13 & 18); an estimate for enclosing the Barracks on the Public Square (1818 April 25); the three gates around the Public Square (1818 May 10); a kiln of bricks purchased by Orris Paine for the public (1818 May 25); the gates, spring, steps, & enclosure in Capitol Square (1818 May 25); the balance of the kiln of bricks belonging to the public & sold for rent (1818 June 2); the request of Orris Paine, administrator of the estate of James Kinkead, to measure the granite steps for the Public Square (1818 June 2); the employment of laborers to prepare the ground for setting & laying the stone around the Public Square & finishing the Governor's stable & public privy (1818 June 13); the springs on either side of the Capitol (1818 July 16); the brick wall separating the Governor's yard & square, the public privy, & the Governor's stable (1818 July 16); the stone wall on Bank Street (1818 July 23); the expense of collecting the water from the springs on each side of the Capitol (1818 July 28); a letter from Orris Paine re. the brace stones & steps around the Capitol (1818 July 28); the claim of George C. Longden for stone work on the Public Square (1819 Sept. 23); the completion of half the work of putting up the braces to the iron railing by Robert Linn (1818 Oct. 9); the contract of George C. Longden for laying the stone around the Public Square (1818 Oct. 10); the certificate of William G. Goodson's work on the public privy (1818 Oct. 25); the certificate of John Segar's work on the brick wall on the Public Square (1818 Nov. 14); the removal of the plank fence around the Governor's yard (1818 Nov. 14); the account of Richard North for marble basins, contracts for completing the public necessary, & alterations to the principal gate at the Public Square (includes small sketch of gate) (1818 Nov. 18); the receipt for George C. Longden's stone work around the Public Square on Bank Street (1818 Nov. 26); the steps on the west side of the Capitol & culverts (1818 Nov. 28); the claim of Thomas B. Conway for drilling holes in the stone around the Public Square (1818 Dec. 1); fixing the marble basins under the steps of the Capitol (1818 Dec. 1); the account of George C. Longden for stone work on Bank Street (1818 Dec. 31); the contract of William G. Goodson for the carpenter's & joiners work on the public privy (1819 Feb. 9); the gate near the Governor's House (1819 Feb. 17); the certificate of Robert Linn for putting up braces for the iron railing (1819 Feb. 23); his appointment as Superintendent of Public Improvements & the inspection of the railing put up by Paul A. Sabbaton (1819 March 16); a sketch of his plans to level the Governor's yard on 13th or Governor's Street (1819 March 18); the certificate of Thomas B. Conway's work on drilling holes in the stone around the Public Square (1819 March 22); his arrangement with Mr. Perryman to open the flue to the fireplace in the part of the room designed for the use of the clerk of the Chancery Court (1819 March 30); the contract of Daniel Calverly to remove the rust & paint the iron railing around the Public Square, and an estimate of the cost to finish the Governor's Stable & brick wall (1819 April 5); posts & chains on the edge of the terraces & coal houses about the Capitol (1819 May 28); his pay (1819 June 12); the certificate of Orris Paine for the setting of the steps of the Capitol & for stone & brick work (1819 July 1); a statement of the cost of finishing the Governor's stable (1819 July 3); a coal house for the Governor's lot & repairs to the Capitol (1819 July 28); an estimate of the expense for conveying the water under the public privy (includes plan of a culvert) (1819 July 31); a report on the state of the public works about the Capitol & Public Square & ashlars around the Capitol (1819 Aug. 17); the certificate regarding the completion of three-fourths of the painting of the railing around the Public Square (1819 Aug. 19); and the certificate of John Kennedy for the completion of stuccoing the Capitol (1819 Oct. 25).
Wilson Bryan replaced Brockenbrough as superintendent sometime in late 1819. Bryan writes to the Governor regarding a report on P. A. Sabbaton's contract (1819 Nov. 19) and a deposit about the Capitol for ash from the offices (1819 Dec. 4).
Both the Governor and Superintendent of Public Improvements corresponded with the various contractors working on the improvements to Capitol Square. The major contractors include Thomas Strode, Paul A. Sabbaton, John P. Shields, George C. Longden, Edward W. Trent, & James Kinkead. Thomas Strode writes regarding his contract with Capt. John P. Shields for all the work to be done on Capitol Square except the steps & stonework (1817 Jan. 13). Strode also writes regarding the contract of James Kinkead for the completion of the stone steps on the Public Square (1817 May 1 & Dec. 30). Paul A. Sabbaton corresponds regarding his proposal & estimate for making a railing to enclose the Public Square (1817 March 10 & 17), his payment & the shipment of two-thirds of the castings (1817 Sept. 30), his third payment (1818 Jan. 3), the cutting of the stone & braces for the railing around Capitol Square (1818 Jan. 22), the railing around Capitol Square (1818 Feb. 2), measurements of the enclosure around the Public Square (1818 Dec. 17), balls & chains for the gates (1819 March 10), the settlement of his account (1819 March 14 & 19), and a request for payment (1819 Oct. 25). John P. Shields writes regarding his proposal to lay the stone around Capitol Square for the enclosure (1817 May 7 & July 11). George C. Longden also writes regarding his own proposal to furnish stone for enclosing the Public Square (1817 May 9). Edward W. Trent writes regarding his proposal to set the stone intended to enclose the Public Square (1817 May 10) and his contract (1817 Dec. 14 & 1818 March 7). Lastly, James Kinkead writes regarding his proposal to furnish granite stone for the steps of the Capitol (1817 June 26 & 1818 Jan. 1).
Claiborne W. Gooch, Adjutant General, corresponds with the governor in his several roles as Adjutant General, Commissary General of the Ordnance Department, Superintendent of Public Edifices, and President of the Board of Visitors of the Penitentiary. As Adjutant General, Gooch writes regarding the resignation of Mann S. Valentine, an officer of the Public Guard, & the uniforms of the guard (1817 March 29); the recommendation for Robert Williamson as lieutenant to the guard at the Lexington Arsenal (1817 July 15); the magazine at Westham, the magazine at the Penitentiary, cartridge boxes & pistol holders stored in the Capitol, clothing for the Public Guard, & the conduct of officers (1817 July 21); clothing for the Public Guard (1817 Aug. 12); his request for records to assist him in the settlement of accounts between Virginia & the U. S. for arms, ordnance, etc. (1817 Aug. 12); the settlement of accounts between the U. S. Ordnance Dept. & Virginia (1817 Dec. 8); the letter of William Price, Superintendent of the Public Warehouse, re. repairs to the building (1817 Dec. 15 & 22); an estimate for repairing the Public Warehouse (1818 Jan. 9); the annual return of the militia & arms, accoutrements, & ammunition for the year 1817 (1818 Jan. 28); an account of the work done in repairing the Public Warehouse (1818 Feb. 6); the conference room used by the Court of Appeals & the skylight in the Capitol (1818 Feb. 18); the guard stationed at the Lexington Arsenal (1818 March 6); a circular letter re. the preservation of public arms (1818 March 7); the furnishing of clothing for the guard stationed at Lexington by the Keeper of the Penitentiary (1818 March 7); recruiting instructions to Lt. James Paxton for the guard at the Lexington Arsenal (1818 March 7); the charges made by the state of Virginia against the U. S. for camp equipage, ordnance stores, etc., during the late war (1818 March 27); Capt. Turner's request for arms (1818 April 13); a small house at the rear of the Penitentiary & an iron grate door at the recently opened passage on the ground floor of the Capitol (1818 May 30); a new artillery company in the 76th Regiment (1818 July 18); the receipts of James Paxton for bounty & contingent expenses (1818 July 20); swords for the Powhatan Troop of Cavalry (1818 Dec. 2); the rank roll of colonels in the militia (1818 Dec. 1); the formation of a new regiment from Nicholas County (1818 Dec. 30); an estimate for the erection of an iron grate door for the clerk of the Chancery Court in the lower part of the Capitol (1819 Jan. 4); the strength of the artillery company in the 27th Regiment (1819 Feb. 3); the discontinuance of military parades on the Capitol Square on account of the improvements (1819 March 22); leaks in the roof of the Capitol & other problems (1819 April 15); the detail of the Public Guard to examine into the condition of the public edifices & property in Richmond (1819 July 16); the consolidation of the 89th & 36th Regiments (1819 Oct. 6); carpets & repairs (1819 Nov. 5); and his duties in relation to public edifices (1819 Nov. 11).
As Commissary General of Ordnance, Gooch writes regarding a report of ordnance belonging to Virginia at Fort Powhatan (1817 May 3); the condition of public arms collected from the commanding officers of regiments in different parts of the state (1817 June 25); the accounts between the U. S. Ordnance Dept. & the state of Virginia (1817 July 21); the condition of ordnance & the gun house near the Penitentiary (1817 Aug. 3); the claim of Virginia against the U. S. for the quota of arms due under the appropriation of Congress of 1808 (1817 Sept. 20); Capt. Chase's letter to salvage shot & shells from the Pamunkey River (1817 Sept. 21); a return of rifles & accoutrements for Capt. Turner's Company of Riflemen attached to the 19th Regiment (1817 Dec. 9); the number & condition of ordnance in the different regiments of the state (1817 Dec. 8); the application of Capt. Hope to exchange arms to be cleaned & repaired (1817 Dec. 12); the transfer of ordnance from Nansemond County to Norfolk & ordnance for the 73rd Regiment (1817 Dec. 22); the poor state of public arms in the different counties (1818 March 2); ordnance stores & camp equipage (1818 July 6); ordnance stores in use during the late war (1818 July 14); an inventory of ordnance transferred by Virginia to the U. S. (1818 Oct. 10); the removal of arms to the Lexington Arsenal & the recommendation that Lt. Paxton attend to procuring winter supplies for his guard (1818 Nov. 27); proposals for conveying arms to the Arsenal (1818 Dec. 24); an inventory of ordnance & quarter master's stores delivered to the U. S. during the month of January 1819 (1819 Jan. 1); artillery pieces in Winchester (1819 Jan. 17); muskets, etc., belonging to the 2nd Regiment (1819 Jan. 17); the erection of sheds for the preservation of ordnance (1819 Feb. 17); gun flints (1819 Feb. 26); transporting arms to the Lexington Arsenal (1819 May 1); a report of arms, accoutrements, etc., in the State Arsenals (1819 June 24); arms from the U. S. (1819 June 30); muskets to the Lexington Arsenal (1819 Oct. 28); and payment for the building of a cannon house in Surry County (1819 Dec. 10).
As Superintendent of Public Edifices, Gooch provided monthly reports on the condition of the Capitol, Armory, Public Guard Barracks, Public Warehouse, & Penitentiary (1816 Dec. [N.D.]; 1817 Feb. [N.D.], March 29, June 26, Aug. [N.D.], Nov. [N.D.]; 1818 March 3, June [N.D.], Aug. [N.D.]; Sept. [N.D.], 1818 [N.D.]; 1819 Jan. 30, July [N.D.], August [N.D.], & Oct. [N.D.]).
Finally, as President of the Board of Visitors of the Penitentiary, Claiborne W. Gooch writes regarding the classification of prisoners & pardons (1819 Feb. 27), rations & the health of the prisoners (1819 March 2), and estimates in procuring a better supply of water for the use of the Penitentiary (1819 July 1).